Mary Louise Mabie Papers 1864-1975
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Mary Louise Mabie Papers 1864-1975
MS 418
Mabie, Mary Louise
Papers, 1864-1975 (bulk 1904-1972). This collection is comprised of the papers of Mary Louise Mabie. The bulk of the material relates to her lengthy literary career. The collection includes personal and professional correspondence, published and unpublished manuscripts, short stories, novels, poetry, a play, articles, and diaries. Also included are research material, legal papers, photographs, and scrapbooks. The collection also contains material relating to other members of her family.
9 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
No restrictions
Biographical Note
Mary Louise Mabie was born in 1904 at the home of her maternal grandparents, James H. and Mary Kennedy, in St. Nicholas Place, NYC. Her father, Webster Boutelle Mabie, was a New York real estate broker and her mother, Louise Kennedy Mabie, was a prolific short story writer whose work regularly appeared in magazines such as The Saturday Evening Post and Ladies' Home Journal. Her parents divorced in 1909 and Mary Louise Mabie was raised primarily by her mother and grandparents. She enjoyed a privileged upbringing: holidays spent in fashionable resorts, a secondary education at a private girls' school in New Jersey, and a European tour in 1922. As a teen she began writing stories and, under the pseudonym Hall Pegg, poems, many of which were published in newspapers and magazines. The Kennedy-Mabie household moved to California in 1926 where mother and daughter continued their literary efforts. In 1928, Mary Louise Mabie's first novel, The Long Knives Walked, appeared in serial form (published in one volume in 1932); she would eventually produce a raft of short stories and four other novels: The Saints, the Devil, and the King (1930), The Pale Survivors (1934), The Root of the Lotus (1938), and Prepare Them for Caesar (1949). In 1948 she and her mother moved to Flagstaff, AZ and resided together until Louise Kennedy Mabie was confined to a sanitarium in the early 1950s. Around this time, Mary Louise Mabie began working as a reporter for The Arizona Republic, The Daily Sun, and Flagstaff's radio station KCLS. She was also briefly married to John "Slim" Ellis in the late 1950s; the union ended in divorce in 1960. After her mother's death in 1957, Mary Louise Mabie achieved little literary success although she worked assiduously on projects concerning George Washington, Alexander Hamilton, and the Earl of Sandwich throughout the 1960s. She was declared mentally incompetent in 1971 and died the following year at the state hospital in Phoenix.
Arrangement
This Collection is organized into 6 series (and 10 subseries)
Series I: Biographical Files, 1864-1975
Series II: Correspondence, 1912-1970
subseries 1: Business, 1913-1969
subseries 2: Personal, 1912-1970
Series III: Writings, 1916-1972
subseries 1: Short Stories, 1918-1941
subseries 2: Novels, undated
subseries 3: Plays, undated
subseries 4: Poetry, 1918-1972
subseries 5: Articles, 1955-1961
subseries 6: Research Files, undated
subseries 7: Legal Files, 1949-1961
subseries 8: Diaries, 1916-1923, 1966
Series IV: Photographs, 1866-1957
Series V: Scrapbooks, 1900-1947
Series VI: Oversize Photographs and Scrapbooks, 1908-1950
Scope and Content Note
Papers, 1864-1975 (bulk 1904-1972). This collection consists of the papers of the author Mary Louise Mabie. The bulk of the papers contain personal and professional correspondence, published and unpublished manuscripts, short stories, novels, poetry, a play, articles, and diaries. Also included are research material, legal papers, photographs, and scrapbooks. The collection also contains material relating to other members of her family, primarily biographical material, writings, correspondence, photographs, and scrapbooks.
Access Terms
Mabie, Mary Louise
Mabie, Louise Kennedy
Women authors
Authors, American - 20th century - Archives
Container List
- Series I: Biographical Files 1864-1975
  This series contains biographical materials associated with Mary Louise Mabie. It includes a baby book, certificates, drawings, news clippings, and material associated with her estate as well as materials relating to her parents and maternal grandfather.
  - Kennedy, James H - General. 1864-1940 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Mabie Family - Portrait. undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Mabie, Louise Kennedy - General. 1900-1957 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Mabie, Mary Louise - The Baby's Biography. 1904-1910 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Mabie, Mary Louise - Certificates and Identification. 1904-1972 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Mabie, Mary Louise - Drawings. undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Mabie, Mary Louise - Estate. undated, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Mabie, Mary Louise - General. undated, 1922-1933 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Mabie, Mary Louise - News Clippings. 1921-1972 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Mabie, Mary Louise - Personal Remembrances. 1972-1975 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Mabie, Webster Boutelle - General. 1894-1940 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Series II: Correspondence, 1912-1970
  This series is divided into two subseries:
  Business (1913-1969) contains correspondence between Mary Louise Mabie and various publishers, agents, and editors. Also included is the business correspondence of Louise Kennedy Mabie.
  Personal (1912-1970) contains correspondence between Mary Louise Mabie and family, friends, and the Christian Children's Fund. It also includes the personal correspondence of various family members.
  - subseries 1: Business, 1913-1969
    - Mabie, Louise Kennedy - General. undated, 1913-1957 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Mabie, Mary Louise - Brandt and Brandt. 1953-1968 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Mabie, Mary Louise - The Daily Sun (Flagstaff). 1954 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Mabie, Mary Louise - General. undated, 1942-1969 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Mabie, Mary Louise - Paul R. Reynolds & Sons. 1956-1969 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Mabie, Mary Louise - Laura Wilck. 1952-1960 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - subseries 2: Personal, 1912-1970
    - Ellis, John ("Slim")- General. 1958-1960 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Kennedy Family - General. undated, 1922-1932 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Mabie, Louise Kennedy - General. undated, 1913-1949 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Mabie, Mary Louise - Christian Children's Fund. undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Mabie, Mary Louise - Christian Children's Fund. 1954-1959 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Mabie, Mary Louise - General. undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Mabie, Mary Louise - General. 1912-1948 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Mabie, Mary Louise - General. 1950-1970 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Mabie, Mary Louise - John Hecker. 1918-1919 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Series III: Writings, 1916-1972
  This series contains the published and unpublished writings of Mary Louise Mabie. The Writings Series is divided into eight subseries:
  Subseries 1: Short Stories, 1918-1941 contains mostly undated drafts of stories by Mary Louise Mabie (including several written under the nom de plume "Webster Boutelle") as well as those by Louise Kennedy Mabie and James H. Kennedy.
  Subseries 2: Novels, undated contains drafts of published and unpublished novels by Mary Louise Mabie.
  Subseries 3: Plays, undated contains a draft of a play written by Mary Louise Mabie.
  Subseries 4: Poetry, 1918-1972 contains writing journals and poems produced by Mary Louise Mabie under her own name as well as under the pseudonym Hall Pegg.
  Subseries 5: Articles, 1955-1961 contains articles and news clippings written by Mary Louise Mabie.
  Subseries 6: Research Files, undated contains research materials largely composed of Mary Louise Mabie's reading notes as well as information on northern Arizona.
  Subseries 7: Legal Files, 1949-1961 contains contracts, copyrights, and royalty statements.
  Subseries 8: Diaries, 1916-1923, 1966 contains the personal diaries of Mary Louise Mabie.
  - subseries 1: Short Stories, 1918-1941
    - "The Ambassador Has a Wife." undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - "And the Finns Came." undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - "Ballerina, Dance." undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - "Bappy and the Ford." undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - "Black John's Rock." 1937 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - "Bracelets." undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - "Bucky." undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - "The Chromium Penny." 1940 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - "Cicero and Cleopatra." undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - "Deb." undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - "The Drinking Man." undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - "Front Street." undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - "The Frozen Piano." undated (Box 1, Folder 39-40)
    - "How Mother Won the First World War." undated (Box 1, Folder 41-42)
    - "Hunger Moon." undated (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - "Luck at Trenton in the Snow." undated (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - "Mr. J." undated (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - "Never Meet a Stranger." undated (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - "No Details" (by Webster Boutelle). undated (Box 1, Folder 47-48)
    - "One Cocker Spaniel Going North." 1925 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - "One Cocker Spaniel Going North." 1926 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - "Someone's Waiting to Get You." undated (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - "Three Days Away from This Town." undated (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - "Thunder Gust." undated (Box 1, Folder 53-54)
    - Boutelle, Webster - "Tumbleweed." undated (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Boutelle, Webster - "Two Stars Collide." undated (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Boutelle, Webster - "The Wedding." undated (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - Boutelle, Webster - "Whipping the Devil Around a Stump." undated (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - Kennedy, James H. - "John Brombacher's Hired Man." 1918 (Box 1, Folder 59)
    - Kennedy, James H. - "Side-Stepping the Clocks." undated (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - Mabie, Louise Kennedy - "The Alaskan Serial." undated (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - Mabie, Louise Kennedy - "And a Man Named Wall." undated (Box 1, Folder 62)
    - Mabie, Louise Kennedy - "The Artificial Moon." 1929 (Box 1, Folder 63)
    - Mabie, Louise Kennedy - "At the Drop of a Hat." undated (Box 1, Folder 64)
    - Mabie, Louise Kennedy - "The Bird of Paradise." 1921 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Mabie, Louise Kennedy - "Come In, Ellen." undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Mabie, Louise Kennedy - "The Doctor." 1934 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Mabie, Louise Kennedy - "The Duchess Wore Black." 1941 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Mabie, Louise Kennedy - "Farthest West." undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Mabie, Louise Kennedy - "The First Mrs. Carrick." undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Mabie, Louise Kennedy - "Five Painted Star." undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Mabie, Louise Kennedy - "Flower of a Chance." 1934 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Mabie, Louise Kennedy - "General Grant's Bedroom." undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Mabie, Louise Kennedy - "John All Alone." undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Mabie, Louise Kennedy - "A Kiss for Mr. Lincoln." 1941 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Mabie, Louise Kennedy - "The Ladies from Colorado." undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Mabie, Louise Kennedy - "Madame Venus." 1928 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Mabie, Louise Kennedy - "A Modern Fable." 1918 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Mabie, Louise Kennedy - "The Tinselfish." 1929 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Mabie, Louise Kennedy - "Willow Street Door." undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - subseries 2: Novels, undated
    - Call Colonel Hamilton. undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Martel. undated (Box 2, Folder 18-19)
    - My Country, My Country, My Country. undated (Box 2, Folder 20-21)
    - The Pale Survivors. undated (Box 2, Folder 22-23)
    - Prepare Them for Caesar. undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - The Saints, the Devil and the King. undated (Box 2, Folder 25-26)
  - subseries 3: Plays, undated
    - Concerto. undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - subseries 4: Poetry, 1918-1972
    - "America." undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - "Bright Ashes." undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - "Bright Ashes." undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Manuscripts. undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Post Card Poems. undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - "The Red Feather" (in Opus Scribendi). 1918 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - "Summer Storms" (in Pacifica). 1972 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Notebooks. 1921-1923 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Notebooks. 1923-1924 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Notebooks. 1950s (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Pegg, Hall - Notebooks. 1923-1928 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - subseries 5: Articles, 1955-1961
    - Arizona Republic. 1955 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Arizona Republic. 1956 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Arizona Republic. 1957 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Arizona Republic. 1958 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - "Blaw Knox at the Dam." 1961 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - "Careful, Pardner - I am Referring to the Town I Love." undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Crime Reporting. undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - General. undated (Box 3, Folder 12-15)
    - KCLS Radio Reports. 1955-1957 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Obituaries. undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - "A Spanish Wedding Near Us in Ciudad Obregon, Sonora." 1957 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - "You can Have Supai." undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - subseries 6: Research Files, undated
    - Literature - Auden, W.H. undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Literature - Boswell, James. undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Literature - Browning, Elizabeth Barrett. undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Literature - Buck, Pearl S. undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Literature - Cather, Willa. undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Literature - Collier, Jeremy. undated (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Literature - Dobson, Austen. undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Literature - Douglas, Norman. undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Literature - Faulkner, William. undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Literature - Frost, Robert. undated (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Literature - Goldsmith, Oliver. undated (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Literature - Greek Drama. undated (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Literature - Johnson, Samuel. undated (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Literature - de Maupassant, Guy. undated (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Literature - Meredith, George. undated (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - Literature - O'Neill, Eugene. undated (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - Literature - Proust, Marcel. undated (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - Literature - Rilke, Rainier Maria. undated (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - Literature - Roberts, Elizabeth. undated (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Literature - Rossetti, Dante Gabriel. undated (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Literature - Sidgewick, Ethel. undated (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Literature - Strachey, Lytton. undated (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Literature - Tolstoi, Leo (folder 1 of 3). undated (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Literature - Tolstoi, Leo (folders 2 and 3 of 3). undated (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
    - Literature - Winwar, Francis. undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Northern Arizona - General. undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - subseries 7: Legal Files, 1949-1961
    - "A Kiss for Mr. Lincoln" ("The Wayward Kiss") - Contracts. 1954 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - "A Kiss for Mr. Lincoln" ("The Wayward Kiss") - Royalties. 1954-1955 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - The Long Knives Walked - Contracts. 1959 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - The Pale Survivors - Copyright. 1961 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Prepare Them for Caesar - Contracts. 1949 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Prepare Them for Caesar - Copyright. 1949 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Prepare Them for Caesar - Royalties. 1949 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - subseries 8: Diaries, 1916-1923, 1966
    - California Diary. undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - New York City Diary. undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Personal Diary. 1916 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Personal Diary. 1917 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Personal Diary. 1918 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Personal Diary. 1919 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Personal Diary. 1920 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - European Vacation. 1922 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Travel Diary. 1922-1923 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Personal Diary. 1966 (Box 4, Folder 21)
- Series IV: Photographs, 1866-1957
  This series contains albums, photographs, daguerreotypes, and several negatives and slides. Subjects include various members of the Mabie family, pets, landscapes, and unidentified others.
  - Flagstaff. undated (Box 5, Folder 1-2)
  - Graffman, Gary. 1954 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - The "John Sherwin." undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Kennedy Family. undated (Box 5, Folder 5-6)
  - Kennedy Family. 1866-1926 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Kennedy Family - Daguerreotypes. undated, 1890 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Mabie Family - Album. undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Mabie Family - Album. 1904-1913 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Mabie Family - Album. 1927-1928 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Mabie Family - General. undated (Box 5, Folder 12-13)
  - Mabie, Louise Kennedy - General. undated, 1895-1897 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Mabie, Louise Kennedy - General. undated (Box 5, Folder 15-16)
  - Mabie, Mary Louise - Childhood. undated (Box 5, Folder 17-18)
  - Mabie, Mary Louise - Childhood. 1905-1908 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Mabie, Mary Louise - Adolescence. undated (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Mabie, Mary Louise - General. undated (Box 5, Folder 21-22)
  - Mabie, Mary Louise - School Photographs. 1910s (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Mexican Wedding (Life Article). 1957 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Military Encampment. undated (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Military Re-enactment. undated (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Negatives and Slides. undated (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Pets. undated (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Residences - General. undated (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Residences - The Little House (Flagstaff, AZ). undated (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Stilwell, Ethel. 1895 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Travel Photographs. undated (Box 5, Folder 32-35)
  - Unidentified undated (Box 5, Folder 36-38)
- Series V: Scrapbooks, 1900-1947
  This series contains scrapbooks relating to the literary careers of Mary Louise Mabie and her grandfather, James H. Kennedy.
  - Kennedy, James H. 1900-1902 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Kennedy, James H. 1903-1907 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Mabie, Mary Louise. 1924-1947 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Mabie, Mary Louise. 1929-1930 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Mabie, Mary Louise. 1930-1932 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Series VI: Oversize Photographs and Scrapbooks, 1908-1950
  This series contains oversize materials from the photographs and scrapbooks series.
  - Photographs - Mabie, Mary Louise. 1908-1948 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Photographs - Unidentified. undated, 1931 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbooks - Mabie, Louise Kennedy. 1921-1931 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbooks - Mabie, Louise Kennedy. 1931-1937 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Scrapbooks - Mabie, Louise Kennedy. 1938-1944 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbooks - Mabie, Mary Louise. 1932-1940 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbooks - Mabie, Mary Louise. 1949-1950 (Box 9, Folder 1)